Guide to the James L. Adams Papers
Stanford University. Libraries.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
James L. Adams papers
1925-2008
1959-2008
SC0949
Adams, James L.
25.75 Linear feet
Papers largely reflect his teaching career at Stanford University and include class materials, correspondence, memoranda, reports, publications, and some photographs (largely of student projects). Collection also includes minutes and correspondence of the curriculum committee of the School of Engineering, 1925-1946.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives Green Library 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: specialcollections@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Administrative Information
Information about Access
This collection is open for research.
Biographical/Historical Sketch
James L. Adams earned his BA in mechanical engineering at CalTech in 1955. He studied art at UCLA them came to Stanford where he earned his master's and doctoral degrees in 1959 and 1961. After a few years at the Jet Propulsion Laboratory, he joined the Stanford faculty in the School of Engineering in 1966. His administrative positions included associate dean for academic affairs; chair of the program in Values, Technology, Science and Society; director of the design division of Mechanical Engineering; and chair of the Department of Industrial Engineering and Engineering Management.
Description of the Collection
Papers largely reflect his teaching career at Stanford University and include class materials, correspondence, memoranda, reports, publications, and some photographs (largely of student projects). Collection also includes minutes and correspondence of the curriculum committee of the School of Engineering, 1925-1946.
Access Terms
Adams, James L.; Stanford University. Program in Values, Technology, Science and Society.; Stanford University. School of Engineering --Curricula.; Stanford University. School of Engineering. Faculty..; Engineering design.; Problem solving.
Collection Contents
- Papers, Accession ARCH-2009-162
  - VTSS Program Materials Misc.:
    - 1970-98 [articles, correspondence, clippings, publications, etc; includes 1970 program proposal] (Box 1)
  - Creative problem solving courses:
    - ME 214, 1970 (Box 2)
    - MS&E 277, 2001 (Box 2)
    - Quality course, 1990-91 (Box 2)
    - Cons. Mind and Memory Oct. 1 (Box 2)
    - Cog. Spec. Oct 6 (Box 2)
    - IE 101/201 (many folders) (Box 2)
    - IE 201 1998 student reports (Box 2)
    - IE 201 misc. photos (Box 2)
  - Creative problem solving courses(cont.):
    - IE 101/201 files 1978-82 (Box 3)
    - ME 121 Student papers 1999 (Box 3)
    - IE 201/ME223 Student papers 1993 (several folders) (Box 3)
    - Misc. student papers 1978-84 (Box 3)
  - VTSS Program Materials Misc. (cont.):
    - Adams 1986-87 (re $) (Box 3)
    - Proposals in response to Questionnaire (Box 3)
    - Program in VTSS (Box 3)
    - VTSS Office Administration (Box 3)
    - Misc. - $ (rumors) (Box 3)
    - VTSS faculty plans (Box 3)
    - MIT – Kaysen 1983 (Box 3)
    - VTSS Administrative Committee (Box 3)
    - Stanford Program in Values, Technology, Science and Society [packet of publications, etc.] (Box 3)
  - VTSS Program Materials Misc. (cont.):
    - Info on S.U. faculty interest in VTSS issues (Box 4)
    - Princeton trip [articles re medieval masons] (Box 4)
    - Budget stuff (Box 4)
    - Senior Survey (Box 4)
    - IDM Review Committee 1987 (Box 4)
    - List of interested faculty from 1983 Questionnaire (Box 4)
    - VTSS / E. Traugott (Box 4)
    - VTSS administrative (Box 4)
    - Misc. Business 1989-90 (Box 4)
    - [VTSS miscellany] (Box 4)
    - [Assorted articles] (Box 4)
  - Robert Textor, “High Tech Bibliography” Version I, May 1989
    - UG courses:
      - IE 100 (3 files; may need to be reviewed for confidential student records) (Box 4)
      - ME-9, 1959-60 (Box 4)
      - ME 107, 1969-70 (Box 4)
      - ME 115A, 1969-70 (Box 4)
      - E9, 1968-69 (Box 4)
      - E-11, 1971-72 (Box 4)
    - UG courses (cont.):
      - E-114 1971-72 (Box 5)
      - E-1 Intro to Eng., 1976-84 (several folders) (Box 5)
      - E-1 – E6 1992 (several folders) (Box 5)
      - ME 121 1998-99 (several folders) (Box 5)
      - VTSS 115 (Box 5)
      - ME 114A 1967-68 (Box 5)
      - E-1 Mfg. Assignments 1980 (Box 5)
      - E-1 Mfg. Assignments 1983 (Box 5)
      - E-1 pre-1991 (Box 5)
      - E-1/VTSS 51 1993 (Box 5)
      - E-1/VTSS 51 1991 (Box 5)
      - E-1/VTSS 51 1992 (Box 5)
      - E-1 Mfg. Assignments 1992 (Box 5)
      - E-1, 6 History slides (Box 5)
  - Quality course:
    - ME/IE 214 assorted files, 1992-2001 (Box 6)
    - 1 file of photographs (class projects?) (Box 6)
    - 1 file of correspondence re Adams’ book publication, 1967-69 (Box 6)
  - Quality course (cont.):
    - ME/IE 214 assorted files, 1992-94 (Box 7)
    - ME 314 assorted files 2007-2008 (Box 7)
    - ME 216A file (Box 7)
  - VTSS 116 War & Technology
    - Assorted files 1990-1998 (Box 6)
  - VTSS 51-52-53 Sloan Course:
    - Early Work & Funding (Box 8)
    - Master copy VTSS 51-52-53 Reader (Box 8)
    - Assignments, etc., 1986-89 (Box 8)
    - Miscellaneous (includes 2 photos) (Box 8)
    - VTSS 51, 1991 (Box 8)
    - Course evaluations 1985-88 (3 folders) (Box 8)
    - VTSS-53 projects (photographs) (Box 8)
    - Hechinger, “The Meaning of Life” (essay on a lecture by Bob Osserman on topology and abstract manifolds), 1987 (Box 8)
    - PEW Grant expense materials, 1986 (Box 8)
    - Schedules and Readings (4 folders) (Box 8)
    - Slide and illustrations (Box 8)
    - Resource material (2 folders) (Box 8)
  - VTSS 51-52-53 Sloan Course (cont.):
    - Resource materials (3 folders) (Box 9)
    - Correspondence, 1982-84, and Sloan essay, 1984 (Box 9)
    - Sloan grants (Box 9)
    - Sloan – Quant. Literary – New liberal arts (Box 9)
    - Sloan / MIT activities (Box 9)
    - Sloan miscellaneous (3 folders) (Box 9)
    - Sloan “stuff” (Box 9)
    - Sloan / Quant. Thinking (Box 9)
    - New Liberal Arts Conference 1987 (Box 9)
    - New Liberal Arts – assorted syllabi (Box 9)
    - Sloan miscellaneous (3 folders) (Box 9)
    - VTSS 51 [course binder, now in folder] (Box 9)
  - VTSS 51-52-53 Sloan Course (cont.):
    - VTSS 52 course binder (Box 10)
    - VTSS 53 course binder (Box 10)
    - VTSS 53 reader and handouts [binder] 1988-89 (Box 10)
    - VTSS 51 reader and handouts [binder] 1988 (Box 10)
    - VTSS 52 course binder (Box 10)
  - Miscellaneous graduate courses:
    - ME214 (Box 11)
    - ME224 (Box 11)
    - ME219A (includes photos) (Box 11)
    - Braille machine (Box 11)
  - Engineering School miscellaneous:
    - 1967 Study (Box 11)
    - Writing & Speaking program 1970s (Box 11)
    - Far Out Stuff (Box 11)
    - Foreign Student Task Force (Box 11)
    - Sch of Engineering Directory 1973-74 (Box 11)
    - Tau Beta Pi Teaching Survey Winter quarter 1975-76 (Box 11)
    - Teaching Improvement Guide School of Engineering 1978 (Box 11)
    - [Unlabelled - Loose materials] (Box 11)
    - Undergraduate Curriculum (Box 11)
    - Ellen Nold – Communications project 1979-80 (Box 11)
    - Colored Billets (Box 11)
    - Course enrollments 1977-78 (Box 11)
    - Manpower Stuff [faculty billets] (Box 11)
    - Planning (Box 11)
    - First Cut, 5 year plan stuff (Box 11)
    - School of Engineering Faculty & Resource Guide 1994-95 and 1997-98 (Box 11)
    - School of Engineering Facts 1993-94 (Box 11)
    - Academic Goals 1960-70 [includes older materials from 1940s and a photo of Dr. Nicholas Minorsky] (Box 11)
  - Engineering School miscellaneous (cont.):
    - Curriculum Committee, School of Engineering, minutes and correspondence 1925-46 [bound volume] (Box 12)
    - Manufacturing Study, memos, etc. 1993-95 (Box 12)
    - Manufacturing Study, Adv. Board presentation slides (Box 12)
    - Manufacturing Study [assorted materials, several folders] (Box 12)
    - Assorted reports, plans, studies [not in folders] (Box 12)
    - Loose materials (Box 12)
    - JLA – viewgraphs (Box 12)
    - Grading information (Box 12)
    - Percent of teaching per quarter 1978-79 (Box 12)
    - Statistics compiled for Pajaro retreat, Spring 1977-78 (Box 12)
    - Slots [billets] Sch. Of Engineering (Box 12)
    - National Conference for Deans of Business and Engineering Proceedings Dec. 1-3, 1980 (Box 12)
    - Assorted SU and Engineering publications (Box 12)
  - Engineering School miscellaneous (cont.):
    - Card file: resource file on information related to improving teaching and learning experiences (Box 13)
  - Mechanical Engineering Design Division:
    - Reorganization (memo and notes) (Box 13)
    - Photographs (mostly student projects) 1970-74 and undated (Box 13)
    - Design Division brochures and publications (Box 13)
    - Loose materials (Box 13)
    - Memo: “To the Faculty of the Design Division” from graduate students, undated (Box 13)
    - Mechanical Engineering division publications, 1992-97 and undated (Box 13)
    - Braille Machine – prints, copy 2 (Box 13)
    - Design: class miscellany (Box 13)
    - Esalen etc.Winter 1967 (Box 13)
    - Adams to Arnold on teaching of product design, 1960 (Box 13)
    - Mexico 1975 (Box 13)
    - Dreyfuss article, final, 1991 (Box 13)
    - Integration of Creativity into the Mechanical Engineering Curriculum: reader and syllabus, 1989 (Box 13)
    - Mfg. Course proposal 1991 (Box 13)
    - The Design Academy: cover letter and summary 2002 (Box 13)
    - Photographs, including those from First Design Div. Esalen weekend (Box 13)
    - Rotary Refuse Reducer Final Layout (drawing) 1970 (Box 13)
    - DD/ME thinking 1995-98 (Box 13)
    - Architecture (Box 13)
    - [Graduate design courses – folder with memo and design drawings 1973] (Box 13)
    - Photographs from a project (Box 13)
    - Center for Innovation at Stanford University (Box 13)
    - Stanford publications, miscellaneous (Box 13)
    - Miscellaneous class materials, correspondence (Box 13)
    - Non-Stanford publications (Box 13)
  - Industrial Engineering:
    - Photographs (events and people) undated (Box 13)
    - Report from the Engineering Management Task Force to the Advisory council, Feb. 4, 1993 (Box 13)
    - IE faculty and staff photos (Box 13)
    - Students [mostly re advisory issues?] (Box 13)
    - IE stuff (memos, reports and others) 1973-75 (Box 13)
    - People (IEEM faculty and staff) (Box 13)
    - IE account 1986 (Box 13)
    - IE miscellany and pubs (Box 13)
    - Progress Report Oct. 15, 1969 NASA Contract NgR 05-020-345 (Box 13)
  - NASA / ASEE Summer Faculty Program in Engineering Systems Design
    - Final reports:
      - Synthetic Carbohydrate; an aid to nutrition in the future 1972 (Box 14)
      - Wildland Fire Management (2 volumes) 1973 (Box 14)
      - Engineering Education and a Lifetime of Learning 1974 (Box 14)
      - Space Settlements, A Design Study 1975 (Box 14)
      - Air Improvement Recommendations for the San Francisco Bay Area 1970 (Box 14)
      - Design Study of a Metropolitan Air Transit System MAT 1969 (Box 14)
      - Planning for Airport Access; an analysis of the San Francisco Bay Area 1977 (Box 14)
      - Project Cyclops, a design study of a system for detecting extraterrestrial intelligent life 1971 (Box 14)
      - Moonlab; preliminary design of a manned lunar laboratory 1968 (Box 14)
      - The SAINT Project; preliminary design of an international satellite communication system 1967 (Box 14)
    - Assorted proposals, reports, booklets on the Program, 1966-76
    - Publicity file
    - News articles
    - Moonlab - draft report
    - Engineering Education and a Lifetime of Learning - draft report
    - Unlabeled file of tables, illustrations
    - US-USSR Marx Exploration Initiative – 2 items 1991
  - Stanford – Jet Propulsion Laboratory:
    - Stanford-JPL interaction (correspondence and other materials) 1959-60 (Box 15)
    - JPL papers (Box 15)
    - JPL talks (Box 15)
    - JPL educational (Box 15)
    - [folder of loose materials] (Box 15)
    - Miscellaneous publications on missiles, rockets, etc. (Box 15)
    - Proceedings of the 3rd Aerospace Mechanisms Symposium, Held at the JPL, May 23-24, 1968 (Box 15)
  - Stanford Miscellany:
    - Ad Hoc Faculty Information Committee 1968-69 (Box 15)
    - CTTL committee 1995-98 (Box 15)
    - Assorted publications (Box 15)
    - Memos, clippings, and other items (Box 15)
  - San Jose Tech Center (The Tech Center):
    - High Technology Science Center 1984 (Box 15)
    - Expo ’85 Japan (mostly pubs) (Box 15)
    - The Tech Center – assorted correspondence, memos, newsletters etc. (3 folders) (Box 15)
  - James Adams’ Correspondence / chron files:
    - Correspondence Sept. 1966 – Aug. 1967 (Box 16)
    - Correspondence Sept. 1967 – Aug. 1968 (Box 16)
    - Correspondence Sept. 1968 – Aug. 1969 (Box 16)
    - Correspondence Sept. 1969 – Aug. 1970 (Box 16)
    - Correspondence Sept. 1970 – July 1971 (Box 16)
    - Correspondence Sept. 1971 – Aug. 1972 (1 of 2) (Box 16)
    - Correspondence Sept. 1971 – Aug. 1972 (2 of 2) (Box 16)
    - Correspondence Aug. 1972 – Aug. 1973 (Box 16)
    - Correspondence Aug. 1973 – May 1974 (Box 16)
    - Correspondence 1974-75 (Box 16)
    - Correspondence 1975 (Box 16)
    - Correspondence 1976 #1 (Box 16)
    - Correspondence 1975-76 #2 (Box 16)
    - Correspondence 1976-77 #1 (Box 16)
    - Correspondence 1977 #2 (Box 16)
    - Correspondence 1977 #3 (Box 16)
    - Correspondence 1978 #1 (Box 16)
    - Correspondence 1979 (Box 16)
    - Correspondence Jan. 16, 1978 – Nov. 26, 1979 (Box 16)
    - Correspondence Jan. 17, 1980 – June 26, 1980 (Box 16)
    - Correspondence July 1, 1980 – Nov. 11, 1980 (Box 16)
    - Correspondence Nov. 11, 1980 – June 23, 1981 (Box 16)
    - Correspondence June 25, 1981 – March 31, 1982 (Box 17)
    - Correspondence 1982 (Box 17)
    - Correspondence 1983 (Box 17)
    - Correspondence Jan. 3 – July 9, 1984 (Box 17)
    - Correspondence 1984-85 (Box 17)
    - Correspondence 1985-86 (Box 17)
  - James Adams’ Correspondence as Assoc. Dean:
    - Correspondence Oct. 1975 – June 1976 (Box 17)
    - Correspondence Oct. 1975 – April 1977 (Box 17)
    - Correspondence Aug. 1976 – Nov. 1977 (Box 17)
  - Stanford publications with entries by Adams marked (Box 17)
  - Non-Stanford publications with entries by Adams marked (Box 17)
  - Adams, Space Technology. Volume II Spacecraft Mechanical Engineering (NASA) (Box 17)
  - NASA Technical Notes D-1211 and D-1351 by Adams (Effects of the Time Lag due to Long Transmission Distances) (Box 17)
  - Adams, Spacecraft Engineering. Space Technology Summer Institute, California Institute of Technology, June 1964 (Box 17)
  - Adams, Space Systems Engineering. Space Technology Summer Institute, UCLA, June 1965 (Box 17)
  - APA talk – program and notes, 1967 (Box 17)
  - Adams, assorted reprints and articles (Box 17)
  - Original newspapers and photocopies of news clippings (Box 18)